Hi.
Someone called '903theBest'
...left a post in ElectroBOOM subreddit
...and asked very good questions,
...so I had to make a quick video.
We know electric current
...is the amount of electric charge
per coulomb, passing per second.
Now, if we get a plastic ruler
...and rub it against animal fur
...and charge it
...and then throw it,
1. Can we say electric current is flowing?
2. Does it create magnetic fields?
3. What's the current flow when
there is a voltage difference?
Where's the voltage?
Is it created when the comb moves?
4. If I vibrate it, does it create electromagnetic fields?
5. What if the charge is stationary
and the observer moves?
Will there be electric potential created?
What do you think?
Pause and think about it.
The answer to all these questions...
[drumroll]
...is yes!
Answer No.1:
Yes.
If we throw a charged ruler,
...it is considered electric current.
If we put 1 coulomb of charge on the ruler
...and throw it at a speed of 1 ruler length per second,
...it will be 1 amp of current.
Now, answers 3 and 5 are related.
Would we have voltage potential
...if the ruler or the observer move?
Yes!
If you have watched my last video,
...you know that voltage
...is the amount of available potential energy
...per unit charge,
...or joules (J) per coulomb (C).
For potential energy to exist,
...we don't need anything to move
If we have q amount of charge on the ruler
...at any point in space or metres away from the charge,
...we have an electric field equal to this amount,
...which has the potential to spend energy
...on any charge present in this spot.
Which means that we have electric potential.
And if anything moves through
the electric field of the ruler,
...no matter if the ruler or the observer is moving,
...we create voltage.
Look at this experiment.
I placed my multimeter here measuring millivolts.
The probes are not touching anything,
...and if I bring my hand close,
...it's not picking up any voltage.
Now if I discharge my ruler
...and bring it close,
...it still doesn't pick up much voltage.
But if I charge it,
...and THEN bring it close,
[chuckles]
Look at that!
I'm making a lot of voltage across the probes.
Isn't it great?
I'm making voltage by manually moving charges.
Now if I stop moving the ruler,
...the voltage drops back to zero,
...because the meter circuit resistance
...diffuses the electric energy at the probes.
But as soon as I move it,
...I have voltage.
And of course the same thing happens
...if the ruler is stationary and I move the probes.
Now let me show it to you on the scope.
I have my scope probe here
...and my discharged ruler.
Now if I charge the ruler
...and move it around the probe,
[chuckles]
You see that I'm creating voltage waves.
Isn't it awesome?
What? You don't share my sense of joy?
Answer No.2:
Yes,
Moving charge or electric current
creates magnetic field.
Let's try it.
I'm passing 10 amps through this-
OW!
[REDACTED]
Hot!
Anyways,
...10 amps through this wire.
Now if I bring my charged ruler close,
...and move it around..
Hmm.
It's just attracting.
The hell?
[REDACTED]
I know.
Well, in a wire,
...the positive (+) and negative (-) electric charges
So the electric charges cancel each other
But in my ruler,
...that
The electric force here is much
stronger than the magnetic force.
If there was only magnetic force here,
...and repel it when I move the other way.
So although it's creating magnetic field,
Do you remember Coulomb's law
from my previous video,
It only works if the balls are stationary.
Ah.
The wire melted the [REDACTED]
out of my plastic clamps!
And finally answer No.4:
Of course if I shake it, it makes it
(electromagnetic fields).
After all, it's filled with charges
And I'm shaking the fields
And of course, moving charges are electric current,
...which makes magnetic fields in space too.
It's funny, though.
...because like I said,
But with this ruler,
Probably more electric than magnetic, even.
It was a very good question,
[Spanish robotic voice]
novecientos tres the best
The wire melted the [REDACTED]
out of my plastic clamps!
No, this was a good question,
But I don't want to spam my channel
So later if I want to make quick, general follow-up videos
...like solving problems and answering questions,
And I'll put a link to them in my website:
So if you're interested to learn
the supplement information,
And of course, moving charges are electric current,
...which makes magnetic fields in space too.
It's funny, though.
In a wire at low frequencies,
...we pretty much only make magnetic fields,
...because like I said,
...the opposing charges are equal
...and pretty uniformly spread.
But with this ruler,
...I'm making electromagnetic fields.
Probably more electric than magnetic, even.
It was a very good question,
[Spanish robotic voice]
novecientos tres the best
Thank you!
No, this was a good question,
...and I thought to make it public.
But I don't want to spam my channel
...with the follow-up videos to
my ElectroBOOM 101 series.
So later if I want to make quick, general follow-up videos
...to my ElectromBOOM 101 series,
...like solving problems and answering questions,
...I'll just make it private.
And I'll put a link to them in my website:
So if you're interested to learn
the supplement information,
...you can go there and watch them.
[our lord and saviour's unibrow dance]
Subtitles/captions by Jonathan Lee (Pentameron)
youtube.com/c/PentameronSV